<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nosql on cse031sust02</title>
    <link>https://cse031sust02.github.io/tags/nosql/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nosql on cse031sust02</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 10:05:22 +0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cse031sust02.github.io/tags/nosql/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My notes about the basics of MongoDB</title>
      <link>https://cse031sust02.github.io/post/getting-started-with-mongodb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 10:05:22 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cse031sust02.github.io/post/getting-started-with-mongodb/</guid>
      <description>Intro MongoDB is a document-oriented NoSQL database. It is one of the most powerful NoSQL systems and databases around, today.
Key Features : Here is the key features of MongoDB :
 MongoDB is free to use. MongoDB stores data in flexible, JSON-like documents, meaning fields can vary from document to document and data structure can be changed over time The document model maps to the objects in your application code, making data easy to work with Ad hoc queries, indexing, and real time aggregation provide powerful ways to access and analyze your data MongoDB is a distributed database at its core, so high availability, horizontal scaling, and geographic distribution are built in and easy to use  src : MongoDB Website</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So you want to start using Redis?</title>
      <link>https://cse031sust02.github.io/post/intro-to-redis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 16:13:16 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cse031sust02.github.io/post/intro-to-redis/</guid>
      <description>What is Redis? Redis is an in-memory data structure server. Which can be used as database, cache and message broker.
Redis = REmote DIctionary Server.
 a key-value store is commonly known today as a dictionary. https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Key-value_database
 # Data Structure Server Data Structure is a particular way of organizing data. Redis is a data structure server. An important difference between Redis and other structured storage systems is that Redis supports not only strings, but also abstract data types.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>